<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<?xml-stylesheet href="style.xsl" type="text/xsl"?>
<post title="Details details details..." date="20090709:202629">
<tag name="plan" />
<tag name="ipc" />
<text>

<p>
I think we have an API decision.  After reading about various event-based
architechures (particularly continuation based systems as used in Scheme) and
worrying that these seemed nice but did not obviously lend themselves to the
uses I intended to make possible, I think I have reconciled the issues.  
</p>

<p>
One possibility is to switch to a completely event-driven system.  Connections
could then be implemented by having a syscall (`connect') to automatedly
register any node as a handler of your event (which will often serve, when
fired, to send all handlers a command which can be processed as a function
call).  
</p>

<p>
This could be placed on the level of the system itself by having all
nodes register their public functions as `available handlers' and then having
any user fire the appropriate event when desired, but this has the problem of
having to setup the interface on the fly, whereas IPC can be made more
efficient if we declare at the outset that we want to talk to the ATA driver,
set up shared memory at the beginning and then use it when necessary, as the
setup is a potential bottleneck, especially for one-off things, whereas the
cost of having many stale connections open at one time is meant to be
minimal.  
</p>

<p>
However, if registering as an event handler allocates space for allowing
transfer of event-related data at the outset, then this is similar to
allocating space for connection data anyways.  Other desirable operations may
readily be simulated with events as well, for example splicing a connection
can be accomplished by the splicer's registering as a handler to the desired
`connection' event.
</p>

<p>
Connections are good when there is a central server (e.g. a ATA driver) that
you want to tell start some task and return the answer to you, but not so much
for other things, like keyboard input, which you want to be accessible to
multiple programs and would thus be best broadcast as an event.  
</p>

<p>
??????
</p>

</text>
</post>
